okay everyone I'm gonna talk to you
today about a book that I'm publishing
in January of 2018 it's called 12 rules
for life an antidote to chaos and it's
going to be published by penguin Random
House I'm gonna tell you how it came
about first and then I'll describe the
book's contents and then I'm gonna read
you a little bit of it okay in 2012 I
did a Canadian Broadcasting Corporation
program called say no to happiness and
in that program my critique the idea
that happiness was the proper goal of
life claiming instead that it's much
more useful and effective perhaps even
for producing happiness to look for
meaning and responsibility in life
anyways I received the following email
as a consequence dear dr. Peterson your
comments on the CBC program say no to
happiness we're both thought-provoking
and challenging they had me asking
bigger questions and that is always
tremendously appealing to be perfectly
honest some aspects were harder for me
to understand than others but I was left
wanting to know more have you considered
writing a book for a general rather than
academic reader I'm a literary agent and
co-owner at the cook agency we have
experience with academics interested in
writing for a broad audience working
with them to remove the scaffolding that
it's required in academic writing and
helping to make their work more
accessible we specialize in selling
authors to international markets and
developing the writing careers you can
find out more about us at WWDC CA I look
forward to hearing from you
Sally Hardy so a literary agent
represents an author and attempts to
market their books and so there they can
be extraordinarily useful people and in
return for that they get a percentage of
the books profits and that's how they
make their living so it's a difficult
job especially now because
the market for books is well very
complicated and increasingly restricted
I would say to a few extremely
successful authors anyways Sally got
ahold of me and I had thought about for
a long time about writing a more popular
version of my first book called maps of
meaning and I actually produced almost a
complete manuscript that was let's call
it a simplified version or I would say
simplified exactly more well I tried to
make it more accessible but I didn't was
never really happy with it I never
really felt that it that it got its legs
underneath it I suppose and maybe that's
because I was duplicating something that
I had already done I was thinking very
hard about what to do about this and how
I might approach it because Sally was
interested in I thought it might be a
good thing to try to write a book for a
more general audience and we talked for
a while and we you know discussed a few
ideas
this was back in 2012 and I mentioned to
her that I had written something for
Quora which is an online website
obviously where anybody can post any
question and anyone can answer it and
then questions are voted on and Korra's
quite interesting I would say and I had
written a variety of answers because I
was playing around with it and some of
them as it always is attracted much more
attention than others and somebody
posted I think it was a young guy posted
this question what are the most valuable
things everyone should know and so I
answered it I listed as it was 40 42
rules to live by and some of them were
kind of amusing I thought some of them
were dead serious and anyways it became
very popular on Quora and as of now it
has a hundred and seventy four thousand
views and 2,500 upvotes which makes it
one of Korra's most popular answers as
it was soon after I posted it and I
thought well people really liked the
rulz there was something about them that
appealed to them so what if I write a
book based on the rules and so I'll read
you the rules okay maybe you'll find
them interesting tell the truth do not
do things that you hate which i think is
a variant of telling the truth because
you have to act out the truth as well as
telling it act so that you can tell the
truth about how you act that's obviously
related to the first to pursue what is
meaningful not what is expedient if you
have to choose be the one who does
things instead of the one who is seen to
do things pay attention assume that the
person you are listening to might know
something you need to know listen to
them hard enough so that they will share
it with you plan and work diligently to
maintain the romance in your
relationships be careful who you share
good news with be careful who you share
bad news with make it least one thing
better every single place you go imagine
who you could be and then aim
single-mindedly at that do not allow
yourself to become arrogant or resentful
try to make one room in your house as
beautiful as possible compare yourself
to who you were yesterday
not to someone else is today work as
hard as you possibly can on at least one
thing and see what happens if old
memories still make you cry
write them down carefully and completely
maintain your connections with people do
not carelessly denigrate social
institutions or artistic achievement
treat yourself as if you were someone
that you are responsible for helping ask
someone to do you a small favor so that
he or she can ask you to do one in the
future make friends with people who want
the best for you do not try to rescue
someone who does not want to be rescued
and be very careful about rescue
someone who does nothing well done is
insignificant set your house in perfect
order before you criticize the world
dress like the person you want to be be
precise in your speech
stand up straight with your shoulders
back don't avoid something frightening
if it stands in your way and don't do
unnecessarily dangerous things
[Music]
do not let your children do anything
that makes you dislike them do not
transform your wife into a maid
do not hide unwanted things in the fog
notice that opportunity lurks where
responsibility has been abdicated read
something written by someone great pet a
cat when you encounter one on the street
don't bother children when they're
skateboarding
don't let bullies get away with it write
a letter to the government if you see
something that needs fixing and propose
a solution remember that what you do not
yet know is more important than what you
already know and be grateful in spite of
your suffering so those were the 40 odd
rules and people were pretty happy with
them and then something odd happened so
a friend of mine as a novelist Greg
Hurwitz and Greg wrote a book that's
become very popular called orphan X and
one of the characters in that book the
female lead I would say off and on again
romance interest for the main character
posted these rules on her fridge and so
they were peppered throughout the book
so that was kind of an interesting
development I thought and then because
they were so popular on Quora I talked
to Sally about the possibility of
turning them into a book and so my
original vision was to write 42 short
essays I thought that would be I was
gonna call the book 42 which I thought
was quite funny because if you remember
the answer to life the universe and
everything from Douglas Adams was 42
a computer calculated that so I thought
it would be amusing to write a book
called 42 that you know contained
answers to life the universe and
everything but when I started writing
the book it turned out that I had more
to say about each of the rules than I
had originally envisioned and so I first
cut it down to 25 and wrote
Messi's and then I cut it down to 16 and
it was still too long and then I cut it
down to 12 which turned out to be a good
thing anyways because if you write a
book you should write way more than
you're going to publish and then cut
because that way you you're only left
with what's best so anyways I wrote for
about three years well no it's more than
that now I guess it's almost five years
because I just finished the book in
September so it took about four or five
years to write and I was writing pretty
regularly what I'm going to do is read
to you a little bit of it I think this
is the book here
that's a galley copy and a galley copy
is a preprint of a book so that you can
get some sense of what it looks like
it's got some nice illustrations in it I
think by this comic book author named
Ethan Van Sciver so that's kind of a
rough one on the chapter 3 treat
yourself like someone you were
responsible for helping Ethan is a comic
book artist he's done a he's a great
illustrator and he put my kids in each
one of my kids I have two kids one of
them in each illustration sort of
contemplating well the complexities of
life I guess that's how you might
describe it so that's one illustration
I'll show you another one so that's my
son Julie and they're looking up at the
great Statue of David and that's part
and that David of course is an
inspirational statue it's a
representation of what you could be and
that's rule three make friends with
people who want the best for you and I
think I'm going to read that some of
that to you right now the each chapter
each rule is divided into subsections
small sub chapters let's say and I'll
read you one of those so you'll get some
sense of the book Rule three
make friends with people who want the
best for you the old hometown
the town I grew up in had been scraped
only fifty years earlier out of the
endless flat northern Prairie Fairview
Alberta was part of the frontier and had
the cowboy bars to prove it the Hudson's
Bay Company department store on Main
Street still bought beaver wolf and
coyote furs directly from the local
trappers 3,000 people lived there 400
miles away from the nearest city cable
TV video games and Internet did not
exist it was no easy matter to stay
innocently amused in Fairview
particularly during the five months of
winter when long stretches of 40-below
days and even colder nights were the
norm the world is a different place when
it's cold like that
the drunks in our town ended their sad
lives early they passed out at snow
banks at 3:00 in the morning froze to
death you don't go outside casually when
it's 40 below on first breath the arid
desert air constricts your lungs ice
forms on your eyelashes and they stick
together long hair wet from the shower
freezes solid and then stands on and
wraithlike of its own accord later in a
warm house when it thaws bone-dry
charged with electricity children only
put their tongues on steel playground
equipment once smoke from house chimneys
doesn't rise defeated by the cold it
drifts downwards and collects like fog
on snow-covered rooftops and yards cars
must be plugged in at night their
engines warmed by block heaters or oil
will not flow through them in the
morning and they won't start sometimes
they won't anyways then you turn the
engine over pointlessly until the
starter clatters and falls silent then
you remove the frozen battery from the
car loosening bolts with stiffening
fingers and the intense cold and bring
it into the house it sits there sweating
for hours until it warms enough to hold
a decent charge
you're not gonna see out at the back
window of your car either Frost silver
in November and stays that way until May
scraping it off just dampens the
upholstery then that freezes to late one
night going to visit a friend i sat for
two hours on the edge of the passenger
seat at a 1970 Dodge Challenger jammed
up against the stick shift using a vodka
soaked rag to keep the inside of the
front windshield clear in front of the
driver because the car heater had quit
stopping wasn't an option there was
nowhere to stop and it was hell on house
cats felines in Fairview had short ears
and tails because they had lost the tips
of both to frostbite they came to
resemble arctic foxes which evolved
those features to deal proactively with
the intense cold one day our cat got
outside and no one noticed
we found him later fur frozen fast to
the cold hard concrete it's no lasting
damage except to his pride Fairview cats
were also at great risk in the winter
from cars but not for the reasons you
think it was an automobile sliding on
icy roads and running them over only
loser cats died that way it was cars
parked immediately after being driven
that we're dangerous
a frigid cat might think highly of
climbing up under such a vehicle and
sitting on it's still warm engine block
but what if the driver decided to use
the car again before the engine cooled
down and the cat departed let's just say
that heat seeking house pets and rapidly
rotating radiator fans do not coexist
happily because we were so far north the
bitterly cold winters were very dark by
December the Sun didn't rise until 10:00
a.m. we trudged to school in the pitch
black it wasn't much lighter when we
walked home just before the early sunset
there wasn't much for young people to do
in Fairview even in the summer
but the winters were worse
then your friends mattered more than
anything so that's a little section of
12 rules for life I could tell you what
the rules are
it's forward was written by Norman
Doidge he comments a little bit about
the political turmoil that surrounded me
over the last year although the book
itself is very apolitical with the
exception of the chapter on
skateboarding where I go into the battle
the ongoing polarizing battle between I
would say the radical left and everyone
else but other than that it's not a
political book so the table of contents
include rule 1
stand up straight with your shoulders
back that's actually a bit a story that
centers on lobsters to a large degree I
I have a what proclivity for talking
about lobsters rule to treat yourself
like someone you were responsible for
helping that's something that people
don't do very well because they're not
very happy with themselves often rule 3
make friends with people who want the
best for you that's the chapter I
already read that I read the first part
of it and it's about trying to organize
your life so that you're surrounded by
people who support you when you're
trying to do what's right it's very
important rule 4 compare yourself to who
you were yesterday and not to who
someone else is today yeah because if
you're comparing yourself to someone
else I mean first of all you don't know
very much about the life of the person
you're comparing yourself to you don't
know in it you know it across all of its
dimensions and second people are very
different and so comparing yourself to
someone else
it's it's kind of useful I guess when
you're young but as you get older and
more singular and more particular it
becomes increasingly less useful better
to compare yourself to a previous
version of yourself and work for
improvement in that way rule 5
do not let your children do anything
that makes you dislike them that's
probably going to be the most
controversial chapter I would say it's a
chapter about
discipline and love and respect I guess
that's probably right rule 6 set your
house in perfect order before you
criticize the world yeah well that's a
rough chapter man that's uh I'm trying
to explain the mindset behind people
like the Columbine high school shooters
and so it's a it's a harsh chapter rule
7 pursue what is meaningful and not what
is expedient expedient is what works in
the short term expedience what's easy
meaningful instead is what sustains you
through tragedy let's say rule 8 tell
the truth or at least don't lie yeah
well it's not that easy to tell the
truth because who knows about the truth
but you can learn not to say things that
you know to be false and if you stop
saying things that you know to be false
then your life will improve a lot
simplifies it and it puts you in the
alignment with reality and you should be
in alignment with reality because
there's a lot more of it than there is
of you rule 9 assume that the person
you're listening to might know something
you don't that's a good one because and
this is even true when you're dealing
with people that don't like you because
they may offer you criticisms that are
valid many that aren't - of course
because maybe they're just trying to
take you down a bit but if you get a
criticism that's valid and then you can
fix that error let's say that'll stop
you from running nose-first into walls
and that's generally a handy thing
rule 10 be precise in your speech yeah
well you have to be exacting in the way
that you describe things and the way
that you think because otherwise you
live in the fog and you won't get what
you should out of life or what you need
out of life and by need I mean what will
sustain you so that you don't become
bitter and resentful rule 11 do not
bother children when they're
skateboarding so that chapters about I
would say our society
Hyper concerned with safety and it's
fundamental antagonism to exploratory
behavior especially among boys rule 12
pet a cat when you encounter one on the
street
yeah well that's about trying to orient
yourself towards life so that even when
you're in the middle of a crisis or a
tragedy you can find bits and pieces of
experience that are positive and
sustaining so that you can stay
positively oriented towards your own
existence and towards existence itself
so anyways that's the book and it's
coming out January 23rd although it's
available for pre-order at amazon.com or
amazon.ca and several other places I'll
put links in the in the video
description if you're trying to figure
out how to orient yourself in the midst
of the chaos that constitutes life then
you might find some of the things that I
wrote in 12 rules for life helpful so I
hope that that was interesting and good
bye for now
you